<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The acts of the diet of Regenspurgh: held in the yeeres 1622 and 1623 Containing these seuerall treatises. 1 Sixe propositions made by the emperour. 2 The consultaes of aduices of the princes vpon the first three of them. 3 The emperours replica to their aduices. 4 Their answer to his replica, with a relation also. 5 Their answer to the three last imperiall propositions. 6 The emperours finall resolution concerning the whole businesse.</title>
            <author>Holy Roman Empire. Reichstag.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03492</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117344</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852559</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852559</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17884</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03492)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17884)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1144:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The acts of the diet of Regenspurgh: held in the yeeres 1622 and 1623 Containing these seuerall treatises. 1 Sixe propositions made by the emperour. 2 The consultaes of aduices of the princes vpon the first three of them. 3 The emperours replica to their aduices. 4 Their answer to his replica, with a relation also. 5 Their answer to the three last imperiall propositions. 6 The emperours finall resolution concerning the whole businesse.</title>
                  <author>Holy Roman Empire. Reichstag.</author>
                  <author>Holy Roman Empire. Emperor (1619-1637 : Ferdinand II)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Eliot's Court Press] for Nathaniel Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Bodleian Library ("Early English books, 1475-1640"), and the British Library ("Early English newspapers).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Diet of Ratisbon, 1622-1623.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17884:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17884:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE ACTS OF THE DIET OF REGENSPVRGH:</hi> Held in the yeeres <hi>1622</hi> and <hi>1623.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>CONTAINING THESE SEVERALL TREATISES.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> Sixe Propoſitions made by the Emperour.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> The Conſultaes or Aduices of the Princes vpon the firſt three of them.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> The Emperours Replica to their Aduices.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Their Anſwer to his Replica, with a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alſo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> Their Anſwer to the three laſt Jmperiall Propoſitions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> The Emperours finall Reſolution concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the whole buſineſſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON, Printed for</hi> Nathaniel Butter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1623.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="acts">
            <pb facs="tcp:17884:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17884:2"/>
            <div type="treatise">
               <head>
                  <hi>The propoſitions of his Imperiall</hi> Maieſtie in the Diet of <hi>Regenſpurg,</hi> made in <hi>the preſence of the two Arch-biſhop Electors of Mentz</hi> and <hi>Cullen,</hi> of the Dukes of <hi>Bauaria</hi> and <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> and the <hi>Landtgraue</hi> of <hi>Darmſtadt,</hi> the Biſhops of <hi>Wartzburgh,</hi> and <hi>Salisburgh,</hi> as alſo of the Ambaſſadors of the abſent Electors of <hi>Triers, Saxony,</hi> and <hi>Brandenburgh:</hi> with diuers others, as here followeth.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour &amp;c. our graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord, doubts not, but that the Electors and Princes here perſonally aſſembled, and the Ambaſſadors of theſe that are abſent, haue by the Imperiall Summons, dated the 29 of Aprill, the laſt yeere, ſufficiently vnderſtood, how neceſſarie his Maieſtie iudged it, to call this Diet of <hi>Regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpurg,</hi> and in it to conſult with their wiſdomes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the preſent dangers of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. But how the warres and other difficulties haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly hindred this meeting, his Imperiall Maieſtie hath by his Letters made apparent to ſome of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17884:3"/> Princes Electors. And for that the Electors and Princes haue vpon the foreſaid Summons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled here at this time, his Maieſtie returnes them all moſt hartie thankes, for their prompt obedience herein ſhowne vnto Ceſar.</p>
               <p>To come to the purpoſe for which this preſent Diet is aſſembled: his Maieſtie holds it not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to rip vp the occaſions, which haue brought the Empire into this diſtreſſe; for none here can be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, of the diuers aſſemblies of the Princes and States of the Empire, made in the reignes of <hi>Rodol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> and <hi>Mathias</hi> our predeceſſors; all which, and the conſtitutions of them, haue to the great ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall of the Empire, &amp; the hinderance of the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Proceſſe of Iuſtice in the Imperiall Chamber of <hi>Spyers,</hi> beene diſobeied and neglected.</p>
               <p>In which calamitie of the Empire, diuers turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Spirits, ſometimes vnder colour of Religion, and ſometimes vpon other pretexts, haue ſo farre interpoſed themſelues, that the tumultuous Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of other Princes haue beene taken into Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction &amp; Leagues made with forem States: To make good which, Proteſtations and Tranſactions haue beene paſſed, and warlike preparations made, not without the great contempt of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire.</p>
               <p>And after thoſe troubles of <hi>Bohemia</hi> (long in plotting) had broken out in the yeere 1618. Of which, the Count <hi>Palatine</hi> (pretending ſtill, That he would haue nothing to doe in that buſineſſe, with the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor, but with the Archduke of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria</hi> only) hath ſhowne himſelfe the chiefe prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor; their Seconds alſo were ſo ſtrongly drawn in,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17884:3"/> that his Imperiall Maieſties Subiects of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> did after the <hi>Bohemian</hi> example, elect the Prince of <hi>Tranſyluania</hi> to be their King alſo; which two acts, haue been the occaſions of the warres euen brought home vnto vs in our owne <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and in ſight of our Imperiall Citie of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereupon certaine of the Electors and Princes of the Empire, perceiuing their Lord in danger of loſing his Kingdomes of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> &amp;c. had in March laſt 1620, in their meeting at <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſen</hi> in <hi>Duringen,</hi> reſolued the Emperour that he might take any lawful courſe to recouer his Eſtates (as their ioint Letters dated the 20 of that March can ſtill teſtifie) yet neuertheleſſe did his Maieſtie herin follow their aduice alſo, that he firſt wrote his Letters ſeuerally vnto them, exhorting them all to deſiſt from medling with any thing that was his Maieſties preſent and due poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>But how little theſe exhortations and threatnings alſo, euerie where in the Imperiall Proclamations dated April 20, 1620. affixed, haue preuailed, you well perceiue, for the warres not only after this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, but the <hi>Turke</hi> hath alſo (by the mediation of <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi>) beene ſollicited for his aid and aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Seeing therefore that the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour for his owne ſafetie could ſtay no longer, nor doe no leſſe; he hath at laſt by the aid and valour of thoſe Princes who approued of the Conſtitutions of the Diet of <hi>Mulhauſen</hi> aforeſaid, and principally of the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> the Houſe of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> not only recouered his owne poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17884:4"/> of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> &amp;c. but for the recompenſation alſo of the great charges of the warres, ſeaſed vpon the greater part of both the <hi>Palatinates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For which great atchiuements, obtained by the aid of the Princes aforeſaid, his Imperiall Maieſtie, in his owne Name, and in the Name of the whole Illuſtrious Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> returnes them moſt heartie and condigne thankes; with promiſe, that his Maieſtie is likewiſe as readie to requite their loues, euen with the expence of his life and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing after theſe victories, the warres had not (as it was hoped that they would) a finall end; his Maieſtie was enforced to ſet out the Imperiall Ban, againſt <hi>Frederick</hi> the Count <hi>Palatine,</hi> and the reſt of his partakers.</p>
               <p>And although the Vnion of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which was at firſt contriued by thoſe of <hi>Heidle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh,</hi> was about the ſame time diſſolued, and the <hi>Palatine</hi> thereby left to himſelfe; whereupon fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the mediation of other Princes for a perfect peace and reconciliation; yet did not he thereupon lay downe Armes; but <hi>Mansfield</hi> ſtill kept the fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and <hi>Iohn George</hi> the Elder (who writes him Marqueſſe of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and who for abetting and ayding the <hi>Palatine,</hi> was alſo proſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with him) ceaſed not to infeſt thoſe of <hi>Sileſia,</hi> and to detaine ſome places in <hi>Bohemia</hi> alſo; the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> in the meane time making into <hi>Holland,</hi> from thence to returne to the warres againe with greater earneſtneſſe.</p>
               <p>For which reaſon therefore, hath his Maieſtie
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17884:4"/> proceeded in this courſe of ſeaſing vpon the Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritances and Dignities of the <hi>Palatine,</hi> that ſo the head of the Faction being diſabled, he might reigne thenceforth more ſecurely, and get in alſo his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys and charges, disburſed vpon the wars againſt him. But to all theſe courſes, did the <hi>Palatine</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid mainly oppoſe his whole power, both by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and his great Captaines <hi>Mansfield, Brunſwick,</hi> and <hi>Durlach;</hi> by whoſe Armies diuers Biſhopricks, and Countreys, about <hi>Strasburgh, Spyres,</hi> and <hi>Alſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> eſpecially were infeſted; and in the Archbiſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prick of <hi>Mentz,</hi> and other places alſo, in the Circles of <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> the <hi>Rhyne,</hi> and the <hi>Landtgrauiate</hi> of <hi>Darmſtadt;</hi> wherein they ſo long proceeded, euen vntill they were finally beaten out, and vtterly van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed.</p>
               <p>But how much his Imperiall Maieſtie hath euer deſired to reſtore ſweet peace to his deare country; the Embaſſies for ſuch a treatie, diſpatcht vnto the meeting of <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> and vnto the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> may ſufficiently witneſſe. Which how much the more he vrged, by offering a preſent Ceſſation of Armes; ſo much the further off were his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies from giuing ouer; but giuing out, rather, that it was to no purpoſe now, to talke of a Submiſſion, ſeeing they were in hand to gather vp a braue Armie.</p>
               <p>To put an end therefore to theſe troubles, his Maieſtie hath once againe (as a ſoueraigne remedie for all) conuokt this Diet, twice before put off. And ſeeing that he could not imagine, that there was any man in the Empire ſo vniuſt, who had the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17884:5"/> boldneſſe to mediate the reſtitution of the proſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed <hi>Palatine,</hi> into the Electorall Colledge (who could not but remember the loſſes he had receiued by thoſe that had taken part againſt him) he could doe no leſſe then to diſpoſe of the Electorate, now <hi>pleno Iure</hi> deuolued vnto him as Emperour; That ſo he might both be diſcharged of his word, and alſo fill vp the number of the Electors againe; all which he had alreadie (excepting only the Inueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which he purpoſed to finiſh alſo at this Diet) beſtowed vpon the Duke of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> in reward of his great good ſeruices, and many victories, perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and obtained with the expence of his treaſure, and the hazard of his blood, for him (the Emperor) againſt his owne Nephew, the ſometimes Elector <hi>Palatine,</hi> in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and by the Riuers of <hi>Rhyne, Neckar,</hi> and <hi>Mayne.</hi> And for that his Highneſſe (he knew) being a Prince of ſingular wiſdome, would be ſtill ſtudious of the good of the Empire; And ſo much the Electors and Princes of both Religions might perſwade themſelues of him, that he would labour by all meanes to maintaine the Edicts, made for the free exerciſe of Religion.</p>
               <p>Wherefore his Imperiall Maieſtie moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly requeſts of this Illuſtrious preſence of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Princes, as thoſe that are of his Maieſties Priuie Councell; that they would pleaſe freely to giue their opinions, namely, how the Empire (which is the maine of the buſineſſe) may hereafter be beſt gouerned, and new commotions preuented or repreſſed, and the moſt wiſhed-for peace vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally reſtored.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:17884:5"/>
               <p>Secondly, it ſhall appeare vnto this Illuſtrious preſence of Electors and Princes, what hath beene done in the Kingdome of <hi>Hungary</hi> with the Prince of <hi>Tranſyluania;</hi> and how heartily his Imperiall Maieſtie hath euer endeuoured, that by haſtning on a Peace, thoſe places, which by reaſon of the ill neighbour-hood of the <hi>Turke,</hi> ſeemed moſt expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to danger, Might be kept ſafe from the feare of an Inuaſion: thoſe often Embaſſies of his ſent to <hi>Presburg,</hi> and the long treatie had with the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſadours in his owne Court of <hi>Vienna,</hi> about that only buſineſſe, can ſufficiently witneſſe. But at length all controuerſies depending betweene his Imperiall Maieſtie: and <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> being redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſome termes of a faire compoſition; and by the treatie held at <hi>Niclasburgh</hi> firſt, and by the Diet of the States of <hi>Hungary</hi> (which continued from May till Auguſt afterwards) a finall peace being concluded; the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire was both delivered from the preſent danger, and re-eſtated in her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer tranquillitie. It cannot be vnknowne vnto this Illuſtrious Preſence of Electors and Princes, how their neuer enough commended Anceſtors, haue beene ſtill moſt carefull, both in times of war and peace, to keepe the bulwarkes and caſtles which are in the Frontiers of the Chriſtian world, in good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, well manned, fortified and prouided: which for his Maieſtie alone to doe, after his great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, and ſpoiling of his countries is moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. Nor is any here ignorant, that the laſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours his Maieſties Predeceſſors, haue not ſince the yeare 1603. receiued any ſuch Subſidies, as might defray ſuch a charge. All which points this Illuſtrious preſence of Electors and Princes ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17884:6"/> do well to conſider of, and giue their aduices there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon; and in the meane time, vntill there may be a generall Parliament of the whole Empire called, to grant his Maieſtie ſo ſufficient a Subſidie, that the Fortreſſes aforeſaid (which it concernes the Empire ſo much to keepe vp) may not either for want, or delay, be expoſed to further danger.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſeeing that as it is moſt manifeſt, that the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> after the end of the laſt Truce, haue reſumed Armes againſt the Houſe of <hi>Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,</hi> their naturall Lords, which they proſecute to the vtmoſt of their power; fauouring alſo and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining the open enemies of his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie; and deuiſing by all meanes, how to lay hold vpon any occaſion of remouing the field of warre, out of their owne countrey into the heart of the Empire; hauing already there made themſelues Maſters of ſome places. Which proceedings of the ſaid States, this alſo hath much aduanced; that they haue brought the greater part of the States of the lower <hi>Weſtphalia</hi> Circle, within contribution; and that they haue not long ſince, neere the city of <hi>Bonu</hi> aboue <hi>Cullen,</hi> raiſed the moſt ſtrong Fort of <hi>Papen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutz;</hi> by which they can now command all that Reach of the Riuer of <hi>Rhyne;</hi> in ſo much that the neighbouring Electors and States of the Empire (whom it moſt neerely concerned) haue beene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to petition his Imperiall Maieſtie for reliefe in theſe difficulties. Wherefore, that this ſo immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent a danger, whereunto from this Fort, the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the <hi>Rhyne</hi> Circle, and that ancient citie eſpecially, (which it ſo much concernes the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire to make good) lie ſo open, may be preuented; his Imperiall Maieſtie requires this whole Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17884:6"/> Preſence of Electors, Princes and Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, to giue their aduices.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, it is vnknowne to none here, with what earneſtneſſe the grieuances of the Cities and States of either partie, haue for theſe many yeeres, and in the yeare 1620. eſpecially, in the laſt aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, beene vrged; and what meetings alſo and Ambaſſies, haue for theſe quarrels purpoſely been ſpent; and what writings alſo, and Iuridicall adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces followed thereupon. Wherefore his Imperiall Maieſty moſt earneſtly requires of all the Electors and Princes, to deliuer their Aduices in this cauſe, how farre (namely) the Emperour may proceed to determine them, without preiudice of his Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Authoritie, or infringing of the Iuriſdiction and ſacred Imperiall Conſtitutions.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, ſeeing his Imperiall Maieſtie hath vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that by reaſon of the daily Reuiewes inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the Imperiall Chamber of <hi>Spyers,</hi> the courſe of Iuſtice hath beene quite hindred; he alſo deſires the Aduices of the Electors and Princes, how this euil may hence-forth at the next aſſembly be remedied, and Iuſtice fully reſtored.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, ſeeing euery man daily feeles to his coſt, the great miſchiefe which hath hapned in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire by the minting of bad moneyes, whereupon hath followed the raiſe of commodities to an ouer deare rate: His Imperiall Maieſtie deſires this Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Preſence of Electors and Princes, to deliuer their Aduices, how this miſchiefe may for a while be remedied, vntill a generall Parliament may op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunely be called.</p>
               <p>And euen as his Imperiall Maieſty perſwades himſelfe, that hee hath in theſe propoſitions, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17884:7"/> the maine of the buſineſſe, which is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted vpon in this following Diet. So alſo, if vpon the Electors and Princes informations, any thing elſe ſhall be thought fit to be enquired of, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie deſires to diſcuſſe that alſo with them; that ſo, ſweet peace, loue, and amitie may be reſtored, and re-eſtabliſhed amongſt the Electors, Princes, and States of the Sacred Empire.</p>
               <p>Finally, his Imperiall Maieſtie aſſures this Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Preſence of Electors and Princes, and the Ambaſſadours of thoſe that are abſent, of his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Grace and fauour.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Dated at Regenſpurgh, the Imperiall Seat appending,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>Ianuary</hi> 7. 1623.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="treatise">
               <p>To three of which Propoſitions of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, the Electors, Princes, and Ambaſſadours, thirteene daies after, that is, vpon the twentieth of Ianuary, vpon mature conſultation, gaue in their ſeuerall Aduices, as here next followeth.</p>
               <p>Our dutie it is (moſt gratious Lord and <hi>Caeſar</hi>) to giue your Maieſtie moſt heartie thankes for that franck profeſſion of your fatherly care of the good and quiet of the Empire; humbly deſiring your Imperiall Maieſtie, (in theſe troubleſome times eſpecially) to perſeuere in that gracious reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>We haue well vnderſtood by the late Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the reaſons alledged by your Maieſtie, for iuſtification of your proceedings in proſcribing the Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> and depriuing him of his Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorall dignitie, with your intention alſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre it vpon his Highneſſe, the Duke of <hi>Bavaria:</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17884:7"/> and that vpon this buſineſſe, and vpon the meanes withall to reſtore a generall and a firme peace, how earneſtly your Maieſty hath deſired vs to deliuer vp our free Aduices, both which we are here at this preſent (vnder your Maieſties gracious correction) readie to doe. After which, part of them ſpake as followeth.</p>
               <p>Conſidering the weight and importance of ſuch a buſineſſe, we thought it fitter to deferre this deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration, vntil the comming of the Dukes of <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> and <hi>Pomeren</hi> vnto the Diet: yet conſidering it might happen to proue but loſſe of time, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect thoſe of whoſe comming we are not certaine: we now deſiring his Maieſty once againe to ſolicite the comming of the Dukes aforeſaid, haue in the meane time thought vpon what we ſhould now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vp.</p>
               <p>Although your Imperiall Maieſtie may ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſeeme to haue had cauſe enough to haue pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed the Ban againſt the Prince <hi>Palatine;</hi> yet are wee of the opinion, that in this particular cauſe, which ſo nearely concerned the diſpoſing of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorate of the Empire, and ſo principall a perſon too, of the Electorall Colledge; the ſudden doing of which might occaſion ſuch great and tedious wars, and dangerous ruines in the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire: that <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould not of himſelfe haue proceeded ſo rigorouſly, nor without the aduice and conſent of all the reſt of the Electors, according as it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed vpon, in the Capitulation Royall, which is holden for a fundamentall law of the Empire. Which courſe of <hi>Caeſars,</hi> euen for the manner of proceeding in it, was exceedingly diſtaſted by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17884:8"/> ſeeing that the moſt doubted not to profeſſe, how that the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> hauing neuer beene ſufficiently and publikely ſummoned, but vncited and vnheard, without all knowledge of his cauſe, and contrary to all ordinary courſe and preſidents of Law, had beene condemned, and againſt all equitie oppreſſed by the publication of that Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Ban. We purpoſe not to call the power Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall into queſtion, yet can we but remember your Maieſtie of that promiſe made in your Capitulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto the Electors, and humbly wee admoniſh <hi>Caeſar</hi> to ſtand vnto his owne word, and not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termit the performance of it.</p>
               <p>As for the diſpoſing of the Electorate, we deſire nothing more, then that we had the power to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Caeſar, with our ſuffrages, but perceiuing ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſo great difficulties in it, we cannot but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh your Maieſtie of the danger of it. This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the opinion of our Electors, that ſeeing your Maieſty hath graciouſly called this Diet for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of peace in the Empire; that it were altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſarie, firſt of all to remoue the obſtacles of peace. And ſeeing that all the ſtirs began in <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, Caeſar</hi> ſhould doe well to labour firſt of all for the quietting of that Kingdome, and command a ſtay to be made of the ſeuere Reformation and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Executions there; that ſo the hearts of the Subiects being ouercome with grace and mercie, might be ſweetly reconciled, and all feare and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt (from which, little good will comes from the people toward their Gouernour) might be vtterly taken away: which thing vnleſſe it be timely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, we ſee no hope either how your Maieſtie can
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17884:8"/> ſit ſure vpon the Imperiall Throne, or how the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Princes can be freed of their feares; there being moſt euident danger, that the <hi>Bohemians</hi> and others being made deſperat by the extremitie of their ſufferings, will take hold vpon any occaſion to begin new troubles, and to inuolue the Emperor and the Empire, with new dangers. All the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> States of the Empire likewiſe, which follow the <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Confeſſion, haue their eyes vpon this <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemian</hi> Reformation, which though it were giuen out to be for a priuate Iuſtice, yet is it ſo linckt with the publike cauſe; that vnleſſe it be ſpeedily ended, and the two Churches at <hi>Prage</hi> (granted by <hi>Rodol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> the ſecond, not in fauour of ſome priuate men alone, but of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and which had continued free vntil the 24. of October the laſt yeare) were againe opened, and the free exerciſe of Religion generally permitted; we ſee no ſure peace likely to be in the Empire, but vtter ruine rather, and finall deſolation may euery day be feared: See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it was moſt apparently knowne, how that it was not thoſe that profeſſed the Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, who begun theſe troubles; but the Noblemen and great Officers, whoſe deſignes the other were compelled to obey. There ſhould therefore be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued an equalitie in puniſhments, but much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it were to reſolue vpon a generall pardon, and a forgetting of former treſpaſſes throughout the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as for the Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> likewiſe ſeeing he was alreadie ſufficiently puniſhed, it were far more commendable in your Maieſtie, that now at laſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſubmiſſion, you would be pleaſed to reſtore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17884:9"/> him to his lands and dignities; conſidering, that if proceſſe be executed according to the extreame rigour of Law, it could neuer poſſibly bee, that ſo long as he liued and had any pretence at all, that euer there ſhould be any peace, but perpetuall acts of hoſtily rather, in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire.</p>
               <p>Touching the point likewiſe of the transferring of the Electorate, this one maine thing were fit to be conſidered of, <hi>viZ.</hi> whither, the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his owne perſon vtterly excluded, that his children, who by the prouidence of their Anceſtors, had before this Act of their Father <hi>Ius adquiſitum,</hi> an hereditarie right vnto the Electorate, or that the Brother of the Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> who hath no way offended your Maieſtie, nor by reaſon of his mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie could not; or other of the kinred of the Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> ſhould be, or ought to be in this caſe negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted: which proceeding would be but hardly taken of other Electors and Princes, and occaſion various diſtruſts betweene the head and the members. The Princes moreouer allied vnto the Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> who had vpon confidence of Caeſars clemencie bin quiet hitherto, now perceiuing all hope of the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of that dignitie vnto their Family vtterly taken away; muſt needs haue recourſe vnto Armes, and endeuor the recouerie of it, by maine force. Againe, if Caeſar ſhould die, this controuerſie being not compounded, it might wel be feared, that many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences would fall out, contrarie to Caeſars deſire. Caeſar now indeed vpon the aduantage of his victories had the Law in his owne hand, but if fortune ſhould turne, he were not ſure to bring it to ſuch a paſſe as he deſired.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17884:9"/>
               <p>Vpon which Conſiderations, wee hold it more wiſedome, to aduiſe <hi>Caeſar</hi> not to proceed too ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly; and hold it much better for him to accept ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the interceſſion of other Electors &amp; Princes, as in ſuch caſes hath heretofore beene done. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering withall, that the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> was as then but yong, and had beene abuſed by ill counſell, and was no wayes the author of thoſe ſtirres in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> all being in an vprore before his comming amongſt them. And that other offenders had likewiſe obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Caeſars</hi> grace and pardon: which if it would pleaſe his Maieſty to grant vnto the Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> he ſhould eternally oblige the whole Electoral Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and all the Kings and Princes any way of kin or allyed vnto him, and the Prince himſelfe and all his poſterity, ſo oft as they remembred this their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile, would be aduiſed how they againe embroyled themſelues in ſuch buſineſſes. Whereas otherwiſe if he ſaw the doore of mercy quite ſhut, and nothing left him but his life, it might be feared, leſt he ſhould for his laſt refuge, apply himſelfe vnto ſome ſuch courſes, as would occaſion farre greater troubles in the Romane Empirie, <hi>Caeſar</hi> therefore ſhould doe farre righter, if for his owne honor, and the good of the Empire, he would preferre mercy before ſeueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and not purſue theſe extremities.</p>
               <p>To all this did the Catholike Princes anſwer: <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> hath ſhowne cauſes enough which he had to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue the <hi>Palatine.</hi> And was himſelfe reſolued, that the Palatinate was now diſſolued vnto him, which he might diſpoſe of without hauing regard vnto the <hi>Palatines</hi> children or kinſmen, according to his own
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17884:10"/> pleaſure. His Maieſty could not wel hold any termes of amitie with him, although he were reſtored: and this impunitie would giue occaſion vnto others to offend. As for matter of puniſhment, there ſhould be no difference betweene the Emperor and the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine,</hi> ſeeing that his Maieſties Lands and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were no leſſe waſted then the others. And yet was there great difference in the cauſe of it, ſeeing that this fell out to <hi>Caeſar</hi> without his demerit; And the <hi>Palatine</hi> did the other, hauing no neceſſity to do it. Hee had refuſed mercy, not acknowledged his fault, nor ſought for any fauour. It is an vnequall requeſt for <hi>Caeſar</hi> to accept of any Reconciliation, ſeeing that his Generall <hi>Mansfield</hi> hath not yet laid downe Armes, by which his Maſter ſhewes, that hee had rather proſecute his cauſe by way of Armes, then to deſire mercy. The ſafety of the Empire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the filling vp of the Electorall Colledge, for which cauſe <hi>Caeſar</hi> had done very well in a ſpeedy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing vpon it, ſeeing that other Emperours had in the like cauſes done the ſame before.</p>
               <p>To which the other party preſently anſwered; That for the ſecurity of the Imperiall dignitie, and the ſafety of the Empire there was no queſtion to be made of it, but that it conſiſted in the concord of the Electorall Colledge with the Emperor. For the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation whereof all diligence was to be vſed, left vpon any diſſention there ſhould ariſe a diuiſion in that Colledge, which might now be preuented by a timely filling vp of it. The Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> hath you ſay done amiſſe, But yet if <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhall ſtill vſe rigor, the Princes of the <hi>Lower Saxony</hi> are of opinion, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17884:10"/> there can be no peace eſtabliſhed in the Empire: the good of which being moſt worthy to be preferred before all other reſpects, <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould doe nobly to ſuffer himſelfe to be entreated, that out of his owne innate magnanimity he would now ouercome him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and change rigor into clemency, by conſenting to haue the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> reconciled vnto him, and make the Empire by that means glad with a deſired peace: otherwiſe there was an appearance of greater danger in it, that the end might proue farre worſe then the beginning, and new flames were likely to burſt forth in thoſe places which God had hitherto preſerued from burning. <hi>Caeſar</hi> had now by the aide of the Electors and Princes, recouered his loſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, wanting nothing but the confirmation and quiet poſſeſſion of them; which this deſired recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation was the beſt meanes to effect. The fortune of warre is alwayes doubtful, and the victory ſo long vncertaine, as the aduerſe party hath power to re-enforce his Armes. And for the renewing of this warre, there was yet a fayre pretence left; for that in the beſtowing of the Electorate, the Prince <hi>Palatines</hi> Sons, Brother, and Kinſmen had bin neglected. And with theſe principles are the minds of the Princes of the <hi>Lower Saxony</hi> poſſeſſed already. The King of <hi>Great Britaine</hi> beſides could not but take it ill, that he ſhould now ſee all his pious endeuours take no good effect, and his only deare Daughter and Grandchil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſtill left in exile. The Kinſmen alſo and alliance of the Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> might eagerly apprehend this neglect of them, to be a great affront, and done in diſgrace of them.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17884:11"/>
               <p>And as for the manner of this reconciliation, there might be a particular Treaty and Conſultation ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for it, wherein <hi>Caeſars</hi> prerogatiue Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall being reſerued, all parties might neuertheleſſe receiue ſatisfaction, and the Empire once againe flouriſh with peace.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, ſeeing that the Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> had taken that miſerable buſineſſe of the alteration of Religion in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to concerne the publike cauſe, whereupon ſo many grieuances and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may follow; we inſtantly deſire your Imperiall Maieſty to finde a remedy for theſe maladies, which elſe will breed no good blood, but heart-burnings rather and diſtruſts, in the Electorall Colledge it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Againe, ſeeing that as it appeares by the diuers interceſſions, petitions, and letters of other Electors and Princes, there had as yet beene nothing done for the relieuing of the ſundry grieuances and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of diuers of the free Cities, we thought fit to admoniſh <hi>Caeſar</hi> of this, that order might be taken for them.</p>
               <p>All theſe Conſultaes diſcuſſed amongſt vs in this Electorall Seſſion, wee haue thought fit to preſent vnto your Imperiall Maieſty, that out of your owne wiſedome you might determine further of them. It is our humble requeſt therefore, that theſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſidered vpon, this Dyet may be ended, and the Empire freed out of all perill, may from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth enioy her moſt deſired tranquility.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="treatise">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:17884:11"/>
               <head>To which Aduice of the Electors and Princes, the Emperor vpon the <hi>6.</hi> of February following ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned this Replica.</head>
               <p>VVEe take it thankfully that you haue taken pains, in conſulting vpon our Propoſitions; and promiſe to be wanting in no one thing, that may aduance the peace and preſeruation of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. We haue in the meane time diſpatcht our Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vnto the Dukes of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> and <hi>Pomeren,</hi> who I hope, will eyther by themſelues, or their Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, appeare towards the end of the Dyet. But you haue in the meane time done very wel, that not ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them, you haue begun your Conſultations vpon part of our Propoſitions. In which Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taes and Aduices of yours, though ſome haue wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heretofore reſolued vs, that our proceedings in proſcribing the <hi>Palatine,</hi> was both legall and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; yet ſome there are of you we perceiue to be of opinion, that according to our Capitulation Royall, wee ought not to haue proceeded ſo farre, without the knowledge and conſent of the Electors. But as we haue no wayes gone beyond this our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulation, but euen before we ſet out the Bann, pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually conſidered of all that was neceſſary to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of; ſo did wee alſo deſire nothing more, then that a Dyet might bee conuok't, for the due treating and aduiſing vpon this buſineſſe: Which Meeting being hindred by the continuance of the warres ſtill proſecuted by the <hi>Palatine,</hi> we could do no leſſe for the taking downe of his courage, then
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17884:12"/> proceed by publiſhing the Bann againſt him, which courſe of ours, ſeeing it was neuer entended to bee proſecuted to the preiudice any wayes of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoral Colledge, or againſt our owne Capitulation, we hope that the Electors will not take otherwiſe, ſeeing that we promiſe withall, ſo to moderate it, that no detriment or preiudice ſhall reſult thereby vnto the dignity Electorall.</p>
               <p>As for the tranſlation of the Electorate, and your Aduice for the reſtoring of the <hi>Palatine,</hi> there is (I perceiue) ſome difference in your opinions. One part wiſely and in fauour of vs, affirming the great reaſon we haue to doe it, and that wee can doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing therein, which is not allowable by the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Conſtitutions, the Chamber of the Empire, and the examples of other Emperors in like caſe. But for the other party, which aduiſed his reſtoring, we purpoſe not ſo farre to conſent vnto it, as to the reſtoring of him to the Electorall dignity, ſeeing that in the diſpoſing of it other-where, we are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that we ſhall doe no more then wee haue iuſt reaſon to doe, as wee haue formerly declared in our Propoſitions; nor will we deferre the filling vp of the Electorall Colledge any longer, ſeeing that no man can be ignorant, how much the diſpatching of it may concerne the Common-weale. And as for the reſtoring of the perſon of the <hi>Palatine,</hi> if you haue any better reaſons to vrge, then you haue yet done, in his behalfe, you ſhall ſee both in regard of his Perſon and his Cauſe (excepting onely his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring to the Electorall dignity) how much our minde is inclined towards clemency, and how farre
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17884:12"/> wee will declare our ſelues, to gratifie the Kings of <hi>Great Britaine</hi> and <hi>Denmarke,</hi> the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and other Electors &amp; Princes interceding for him.</p>
               <p>Now as concerning our forbidding of the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Lutheran Religion in the City of <hi>Prage,</hi> we doe not ſee how it any way concernes this Dyet to enquire of; our Letters haue ſignified the cauſes that moued vs to beginne it, vnto the Elector of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xony:</hi> nor can wee thinke, that what wee haue done there, any of the neighbour States or Territories need be ſuſpitious of, ſeeing that we haue ſworn oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then once, in the word of an Emperor, that wee will moſt religiouſly obſerue the peace both of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and of ciuill gouernment throughout the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, nor will we ſuffer any others any wayes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe it.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, as for the grieuances of the Imperiall and Hans-townes, wee very well remember as yet the ſincere promiſes, aſſurances, and tranſactions; as alſo of that we agreed vnto at Treaty of <hi>Aſchaffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bug.</hi> All which we haue hitherto beene moſt carefull to obſerue moſt religiouſly, and ſo ſtill ſhall be, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we finde cauſe to the contrary, that ſo all cauſe of complaint may finally bee taken away from the Cities. And thus much wee could not but aduertiſe this Illuſtrious preſence of Electors and Princes, and you the Ambaſſadors of thoſe that are abſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="treatise">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17884:13"/>
               <head>To this Replica (or Reply) of the Emperour, the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Princes returned this following anſwer, vpon the <hi>21.</hi> of February, ſubioyning withall a Relation vnto his Maieſty.</head>
               <p>VVEE haue (gracious Lord and Emperor) conſulted amongſt vs in our common Councell, vpon your Maieſties Reply, which wee ſuppoſe worthy your ſeeing. But paſſing ouer in the meane to aduiſe vpon your three latter Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we found this to be the firſt and maine point; what (namely) were beſt to be done, that the whole Empire might with the Emperour enioy a ſolid peace; vpon which it was the aduice of one party of vs, that ſeeing the proſcribed <hi>Mansfield</hi> is the man who hath ſo much infeſted the Empire, wee of that party aduerſe to him, haue thought vpon the way to auert and take him downe; which is, to aduiſe <hi>Caeſar</hi> to employ his Army Royall againſt him; by the force of which, and the ayd of the neighbouring Princes and States, required by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> hee may bee driuen out of the bounds of the Empire; and all his ſouldiers which ſhall continue obſtinate, may by a publike Edict of proſcription, and confiſcation, bee deterred from Armes; and the neighbours may be forbidden any way to ayd him, and commanded to proſecute him, according to the vttermoſt of their power. Which courſe if it bee taken, and all the States of the Empire withall, put in mind of their dutie to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and of thoſe Conſtitutions which may concerne either Religion or Peace; we doubt not but that euery man may after that, enioy his owne reſt and tranquilitie.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:17884:13"/>
               <p>Further, as concerning that contribution to bee imployed vpon the making good of the confines of the Empire againſt the Turke, we would willingly follow the pious examples of our Anceſtors in that kind; and yet know wee not how of our ſelues to conſent vnto it, vntill the matter may more fully be treated vpon, in the next Dyet. But conſidering withall the miſerable waſte that hath beene of late made in your Maieſties Prouinces, and that your Treaſury hath not for ſome yeares beene ſupplied by any contribution raiſed in the Empire, wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not thinke this requeſt of <hi>Caeſars</hi> any way vniuſt; and much deſire that we were able herein to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie <hi>Caeſar.</hi> But ſeeing withall how apparent it is, what continuall aydes wee haue faithfully lent vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and what charges, far greater then the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary contributions, with the hazard too of our own Countries, we haue beene at, for the recouery of <hi>Caeſars</hi> dignities; and are now ſtill forced to bee at, for the diuerſion of the imminent warres; and that in the end, ſo particular and ſmall a contribution as wee are able to affoord, could not much aduance that deſigne; we hope that <hi>Caeſar</hi> will hold vs excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed if wee cannot herein affoord him that content which we willingly would. But if this Propoſition might be made to all the States of the Empire, wee doubt not but they would be found very willing and ready vnto it.</p>
               <p>As concerning your Maieſties third Propoſition, of the dangerous reſolution of the vnited Prouinces for remouing the field of warre into the Empire, and their late attempts in <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> and their building
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17884:14"/> of the Fort of <hi>PapenmutZ</hi> in the Rhyne, betwixt <hi>Bon</hi> and <hi>Cullen;</hi> we cannot but commend your fatherly care; nor are we ignorant that diuers conſultations haue beene had about it, in ſome former Dyets alſo; where it was ſtill found that the forces of any one State were not able to hinder the Low Country-men, nor can we now agree vpon the meanes of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. And as for <hi>Papenmutz,</hi> your Maieſty is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of it, as of a piece now taken in by the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducheſſe her forces; and if it were not vpon this quite demoliſhed, there would be much danger in it, that it would not onely hinder all commerce by the Rhyne, but alſo that the Hollanders would ſome where elſe raiſe another to confront it, which would breed great diſcommodities both to the neighbour States, and to the whole Empire. Our earneſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt therefore in this point is, That your Maieſty would intercede with the Archducheſſe, for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantleing and vtter raſing of that Caſtle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And this is the effect of what was deliuered, by the Catholike Electors and Princes; what next followes is belonging vnto this Anſwer to the Imperiall Replica al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, but made apart by the Saxiſh and Brandenburghers Ambaſſadors, and Lodowicke Landtgraue of Darm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtadt, perſwading rather to proceed by the way of peace, as here followes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our voyces and aduices (gracious Lord and <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi>) which we haue giuen before,<note place="margin">See before in their aduice to the Emperors Propoſitions.</note> concerning the proſcribing of the Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> and the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Electorate, we know to be founded vpon the beſt examples, and the immoueable Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of the Empire, and were meant to no other
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17884:14"/> end, then that concord and confidence being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed betwixt all the States of the Empire, the warres may be laid downe, peace reſtored, the whole State being aſſured to the Emperor in the bond of Peace, all may bee conuerted to the confirming of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the commodity of the States, and the terror of all the Enemies of the Empire: And we doe hope that <hi>Caeſar</hi> will ſo interpret vs.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe other points contained in the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Propoſitions; as the dangerous hoſtility vſed by <hi>Mansfield,</hi> and the attempts of the States of the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> in <hi>Weſtphalia</hi> and other places ſubiect to the Elector of <hi>Cullen,</hi> we are much vext and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, to ſee ſuch principall members of the Empire ſo much afflicted; and doe confeſſe, that vnleſſe that wholſome way of Peace be ſpeedily taken, and that flame of war timely quencht by the waters of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, there can nothing come of it, but vtter ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and combuſtion in the Empire. Tis at <hi>Caeſars</hi> choice to take other mens aduices alſo in this point, and wee doubt not but they will all giue him ſuch counſell as may beſt conduce to this purpoſe. But for our owne parts, wee hold the way of peace for the beſt and ſafeſt, as wee ſhewed in our former ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, which wee earneſtly wiſh might with all the clauſes and particulars in it, be formerly called to mind againe, and rightly and timely apprehended; that all iealouſies might ſo be remoued, and peace reſtored: without which, things will neuer ſucceed rightly for the ſafety of the Empire. It cannot be thought but what the P. <hi>Palatine</hi> hath done might well trouble your M<hi rend="sup">tie</hi>: yet we hope <hi>Caeſar</hi> wil rather
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17884:15"/> reſpect peace, ſpare his loyall ſubiects, take into his pittie the millions of miſeries which the warres oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and out of a magnanimitie, worthy of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> adde this to the reſt of his victories, that he will now ouercome himſelfe, and ſuffer his owne inbred cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, his loue to the publike good, the ſafetie of the Empire, and the generall quiet of all men; to beare ſome ſway with him, and make by this meanes his owne name immortall to all poſterities.</p>
               <p>As for that reformation already begunne in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> what danger and deſpaire did by reaſon of that, at this preſent hang ouer that kingdome, his Highneſſe, the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> had often intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and admoniſht him likewiſe of the dangers redounding thence vnto the neighbour Countries. Wee therefore here once againe moſt humbly ſue vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that he would pleaſe to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer himſelfe to bee entreated, and giue way to the the moſt waighty reaſons brought to perſwade him, and that he would forbeare that worke of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſet open the Proteſtants Churches, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the free exerciſe of Religion, according to the <hi>Auguſtane</hi> Confeſſion; that hee would pardon the ſubiect, and vniuerſally forgiue and forget, prefer mercie before rigour of law, and ſo moſt firmely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige the minds of the Subiect, in loue, duty, and deuotion vnto him.</p>
               <p>As for the complaints of the free Cities, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Empire, wee thinke it fit, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> might be certified of their particular grieuances, by their ſeuerall petitions: that ſo they might with all ſpeed be caſed of that burden of maintaining the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17884:15"/> ſouldiers, the gouernment of the Cities, fully again reſtored vnto the Magiſtrates, all exactions left off, promiſes and couenants kept, treaties ratified, and all miſchiefe auerted; ſeeing that it ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the weale publike to preſerue theſe Cities in the deuotion of <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What the Electors of <hi>Saxony</hi> and <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> thought in the point of the proſcription, appeared by their former aduice vpon it. But ſeeing that in an after Relation of it, theſe words were added which were not in the former; which were, That the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour might doe it <hi>Abſolutely and without being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the manner.</hi> The Electors could not forbeare from oppoſing themſelues againſt it; for that it no waies agreed with the Capitulation Royall, ſeeing that thoſe things vnto which <hi>Caeſar</hi> binds himſelfe by that Capitulation, are not <hi>ſimply, abſolutely, and without being preſcribed the manner,</hi> in his power: nor can the Electorall dignitie for this reaſon bee preſerued ſafe &amp; entire vnto the perſons. The words of the Capitulation are clear: <hi>In all difficult buſineſſes, no proceſſe ought to be made, without the knowledge &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the Electors; &amp; that without ordinary Proceſſe, no Proſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould go out againſt any one of the States of the Empire, before the cauſe were heard.</hi> This is the fundamentall Law of the Empire, which requires no more, but to be conſtantly obſerued, nor is it to bee drawne into further diſpute or deliberation: but it ſtood the Electors vpon to bee open eyed to ſee to the obſeruation of it; and it concerned the three ſecular Electors eſpecially, whoſe dignitie did by an hereditary right deſcend vnto their poſteritie, to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17884:16"/> keepe it ſafe and entire; which they hoped that <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> would not goe about to contradict.</p>
               <p>As for that which was aduiſed by the Catholike Electors and Princes, concerning the raſing of the Fort of <hi>Papenmutz,</hi> we will ſay nothing, ſeeing that we haue not before this had any relation of the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it: onely wee deſire the Catholike Electors and Princes to perſwade themſelues, that wee no way enuy their ſafety.</p>
               <p>As for that contribution, and the reſtraining of the States of the Low Countries, we thus far forth agree with the reſt, that it ought to bee referred to the future Dyet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="treatise">
               <head>To this Anſwer they all ſubioyned a Relation, wherein you haue the minds of the Catholike Princes ioint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together, and that of the Electors of Saxony, and Brandenburgh, &amp; the Landtgraue of Darm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtadt, each ſeuerally by themſelues. The Catholike Princes begin: in which they come nearer to the termes of peaceable proceedings.</head>
               <p>IT ſeemed moſt neceſſary vnto vs (moſt gracious Lord and <hi>Caeſar</hi>) in our conſultations vpon your Imperiall Replica, to exhibite the ſumme of all vnto your Maieſty, as followeth: We haue taken it into our conſideration, That if both parties in this Dyet ſhall ſtill perſiſt in aduiſing contrary cauſes, and no middle termes be found out, vpon which wee may both agree and conioyne our voyces, there may bee much danger in it, that this ſo long expected Dyet, muſt breake vp at laſt without any good end, which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17884:16"/> will be for euer vnexcuſable, ſeeing that ſo many eyes both within and without the Empire, are caſt vpon it, looking after this, to ſee either the ſure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, or the vtter ruine of the Empire: we haue thought it fitteſt to admoniſh <hi>Caeſar</hi> to continue conſtant vnto that purpoſe of his concerning the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> into grace, (excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting onely the reſtoring of him to his Electorall Dignity) which reſolution hath beene created in your Maieſty, by the earneſt interceſſions and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties of ſo many Princes. (Prouided, that his due ſubmiſſion and declaration of his obedience be firſt manifeſted) that ſo there may be left ſome hope vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Prince of an entire reconciliation.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing that the King of <hi>England</hi> hath requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that there might ſtill be ſome reſpect and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration had to his Grandchildren, and that there haue beene ſome motions made of the pretences of the neere kindred of the Prince aforeſaid, in our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer conſultations: We moſt humbly beſeech <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> to conſent vnto the reconciliation of the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Grandchildren; and that time and place may be ſet to the Princes kinſmen, to purſue their ſeuerall pretences, either by the way of a friendly comprimiſe, or by courſe of law.</p>
               <p>And if your Maieſty be ſtill reſolute to transferre his Electorate vpon the Duke of <hi>Bauaria,</hi> and bee firmly of the mind, that this proceeding ſhal neither bee contrary vnto the golden Bull, nor to your owne Capitulation Royall; yet that you would bee entreated ſo to moderate the buſineſſe, that it may no wayes appeare preiudiciall vnto the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17884:17"/> Grandchildren of the King of <hi>England,</hi> and vnto the Prince <hi>Palatines</hi> other Kinſmen.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing that the many vertues, and heroicall minde of the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and his care for the aduancement of Iuſtice, and of the peace of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire are ſufficiently knowne: wee hope his Highnes will not take it ill, to be timely admoniſhed of the whole buſineſſe, and of the dependancies of it.</p>
               <p>After this, the Ambaſſadors of the Elector of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xony</hi> ſpake as followeth: How well affected our Lord and Maſter is to peace, appeares by the reaſons laid downe in our former Aduice; which reaſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo grounded vpon the Conſtitutions of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, they Lawes, Cuſtomes, and beſt Examples, that they deſerue not to be neglected; which if they might once take place, wee doe not doubt but they would proue very beneficiall. For our ſelues we are tied to our inſtructions: ſo that it cannot be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our faults if we goe no further then we haue ſaid before. For this is the conſtant opinion of our Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, That the meanes of obtaining the moſt deſired Peace, conſiſts not in the tranſlation of the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, but in the reſtitution of the Prince <hi>Palatine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Ambaſſadors of the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> ſpake next: Our former Aduice expreſſes ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what way our Lord and Maſter holds beſt for the reſtoring of Peace. And ſeeing wee haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued no further Command, to approue of any other courſe, wee can now ſay no otherwiſe then what wee haue done in our Aduice; which was, ſtill to vrge the reſtoring of the Prince Elector <hi>Palatine,</hi> and to affirme, that the tranſlation
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17884:17"/> of the Electorate, is no meanes of peace. And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that for want of any further Command, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſent to no other Courſe; We hold, that the meanes propoſed by our Elector (all being well as yet) is the beſt courſe both to aſſure, the honor and obedience due vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and to recover the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall peace of the Empire.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, ſpake the Landtgraue of <hi>Darmſtadt.</hi> See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Tranſlation of the Electorate pertaines to the whole Colledge of the Electors to diſpoſe of, I therefore thinke it fitteſt to referre it thither. And ſeeing that the generall quiet of the Empire is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed by that Bohemian Reformation; it is my opinion, that all the Electors and Princes would moſt humbly perſwade with <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to remedy that, after which I dare aſſure my ſelfe, that all the reſt of our Deſignes, will ſucceed the better.</p>
               <p>And theſe were the things, which the Electors and Princes had then reſolved to exhibite vnto <hi>Caeſar.</hi> To whom, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The next day being the 22. of February; they thus gaue in their Anſwere to the three laſt Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Propoſitions.</p>
               <p>Wee cannot omit (moſt gracious Lord and <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi>) to giue vp our Advice alſo, vpon thoſe heads of your Maieſties Propoſitions, which concerne the remedying of the grievances ſo oft complained vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Reſtitution of Iuſtice, and the calling in of the Coines of baſe allay, vnto the Standard. All which, that they may be now remedied, after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny meetings, and conſultations vpon them, which haue ſtill beene diſturb'd and broken off, by theſe troubles; is our earneſt Prayer.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17884:18"/>
               <p>As for the grievances of the Citties, ſeeing they concerne ſo many ſeverall States, without whoſe particular information and adviſe, they can neither be ſufficiently knowne, nor remedied; We thinke it fit, that all their Councels were askt vpon it.</p>
               <p>As for the courſe of juſtice, now vtterly oppreſſed almoſt in the Emperiall Chamber of <hi>Spyers,</hi> which having beene the fountaine of ſo many miſchiefes, and confuſions, now ſo rife in the Empire, &amp; which (vnleſſe Iuſtice be timely relieved) will no doubt breed more. It is our duties to aſſiſt our Emperour in ſuch a difficultie, which ſo neerely concernes his Crowne and dignitie, with our beſt counſayles and helpes, for the reviving of juſtice, which lyes now a dying. Tis well knowne whence this corruption of juſtice began, and that it lyes not in the power of a few, to remedy it. For which cauſe we hold it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to referre this over to a generall Dyett.</p>
               <p>And yet is it nevertheleſſe, the opinion of ſome of vs, that this will both much advance the Peace, and eaſe the Citties, and the towne of <hi>Spyers</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally (which is the port of Iuſtice, to which every man puts in) now ſo over-charged with Garriſon: if that <hi>Caeſar</hi> would timely take it into his care, to make a fit ſupply of the voyd places of the Iudges there, which haue vſed ſtill to be fetcht out of the <hi>Weſtphalian</hi>-Circle.</p>
               <p>And as for the embaſing of the moneyes and how every man ſeeking for his private Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, takes advantage vpon it, and of the irrecoverable damage from thence redounding vnto the Empire, it were but ſuperfluous to rip vp, conſidering how evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the encreaſe of theſe miſchiefes was to be ſeene:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17884:18"/> for which enormities if a ſpeedie courſe were not taken, farewell then the glory and wealth of the Romane Empire.</p>
               <p>And although ſome Princes Ambaſſadors there, were firmely of the mind, that this alſo belonged vnto a generall Dyet; yet notwithſtanding, ſeeing that certaine States of the Empire had adviſedly conſidered vpon it; and had alreadie done ſome good that way in the Empire; namely, by an Edict publiſhed Anno 1595. whereby the gold and ſilver Coynes of greater value, were reduced vnto their iuſt worth; and the ſmaller and baſer, quite calld in: there is no doubt, but if other Citties, and thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially which haue yearely Marts, and great Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, were envited vnto this courſe; and that <hi>Caeſar</hi> alſo would take the like order in his owne Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; that this evill would be well enough provided for.</p>
               <p>Another part of vs alſo thinke it fit to referre thus much vnto <hi>Caeſars</hi> owne wiſedome and libertie, that beſides the calling downe, and calling in of the bad moneyes, and the new Coyning of others, which ſhould be according to the conſtitutions of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; that a Rate may alſo be ſet vpon all Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities and Sales, proportionable vnto the valew of the Moneyes. For ſeeing that this great abuſe was firſt brought in by a few, which proved generall by degrees; ſo there is no doubt, but that if this Reduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were to be generally obeyed, others would be wary of looſing by bad moneys; which would make the meanes for the remedying of theſe abuſes, the more facile and apparent, againſt the next generall Dyett. All which we ſubmit, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="treatise">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:17884:19"/>
               <head>To this Anſwere and Relation, his Imperiall Maieſtie the next day being the <hi>23.</hi> of February, gaue his finall Reſolution, as here followeth.</head>
               <p>OVR moſt gracious Lord the Romane Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, &amp;c. hath received the Anſweres of the Electors, Princes, and Ambaſſadors vnto his Imperiall <hi>Replica,</hi> with an humble relation beſides; whereby he well vnderſtands their deſires for the reſtoring of the <hi>Palatine;</hi> Now his Imperiall Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie could haue wiſhed, that the ſaid baniſhed <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> after ſo many admonitions, had by his ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made himſelfe capeable, of his Imperiall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour: Wherefore his Maieſtie hath alſo taken in good part the former letters of the Electors of Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony and Brandenburgh, written in favour of him. But conſidering on the other ſide, the manifolde treſpaſſes of the <hi>Palatine</hi> aforeſaid, his Maieſtie ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines that he cannot be thought any way to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, if he executes Iuſtice, to the terror and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of others.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſſe, that it may appeare, how farre his Imperiall Maieſtie (as a Lord that meanes well) is willing to condeſcend vnto the earneſt Interceſſion of the Princes of the Empire, and yeeld vnto the ſo much deſired mercy; and how well he is inclined to conſider deliberately, of thoſe difficulties and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, which haue with a good meaning beene fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt by them. His Maieſty herevpon declareth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be well enough content (ſo far forth as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth his ſuffering of the <hi>Palatine</hi> to be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto him) for the ſakes of thoſe Kings, Electors, and Princes, who haue interceded for him; and to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17884:19"/> giue demonſtration therewithall, of his Maieſties owne good and peaceable diſpoſition: namely, that his Maieſtie is content vpon the due ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, deprecation, and preſent demonſtration of his due obedience, Faith, and Allegeance, and his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting withall, from any warlike preparations, to grant him the Reconciliation, as the caſe ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: Excepting onely his admiſſion vnto the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorall dignity. Truſting, that thoſe who haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceded for the <hi>Palatine,</hi> will alſo perſwade him, that not neglecting his Royall grace and mercy, he doe not againe depriue himſelfe of the benefit of it, by deferring his ſubmiſſion; but that he embrace it with due thankfulnes, and demeane himſelfe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
               <p>And for as much as concerneth the Palatines children, and their future iſſue, as alſo his next kinſmen, and their pretended right vnto the Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torate and Inheritance: The Electors and Princes haue well vnderſtood the reaſons which moved his Maieſtie to deprive them, by the Imperiall Bann, which cannot now bee altered. But as it never was his Maieſties intention, to doe any thing in preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the Electorall preheminencie, the Imperiall capitulation, the golden Bull, or any other of the Conſtitutions of the Empire: So likewiſe will not his Maieſtie cut off or debarre any man from his right. But ſeeing that there be diverſe pretenders, who lay claime vnto it: as amongſt the reſt, the <hi>Palatines</hi> children, brother, and others of his kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; they ſhall all remaine ſtill vnpreiudiced in their pretenſions. For, (ſeeing that the afore men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Pretenders haue not hither to given in their
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17884:20"/> names, nor appeared in it) this controverſie can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee determined, ſo ſuddenly as they would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it ſhould. And ſeeing that ſo many chaunces may vnexpectedly fall out, his Maieſtie cannot, nor will not, beare the Electors place voyde and vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided any longer, (and is once for all much leſſe reſolved to reſtore it, now or at any other time, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the perſon of proſcribed <hi>Palatine:</hi>) but will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently inveſt the Illuſtrious Prince the Duke of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia,</hi> with the Electorall dignity, in reward of his many good ſervices done vnto <hi>Caeſar:</hi> as hath bin ſufficiently ſhowne in the Imperiall propoſitions.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſſe, to ſhew withall a ſingular favour vnto the King of England, and to divers other Potentates, Electors, Princes and States, as likewiſe to thoſe principally that are here preſent, who haue all interceded for the <hi>Palatine;</hi> his Maieſtie is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſhew thus much mercy to the children of the <hi>Palatine</hi> and their future iſſue, and next kinſmen in their ſeverall pretenſions, as well to the Electorate, as to the inheritance of the <hi>Palatine;</hi> that there ſhall be a meeting appoynted at ſome convenient place, as namely, at Norimberg, Franckford, Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bugh, or Vlme; where in loue and friendſhip the buſineſſe ſhall bee treated vpon, &amp; there decided in the name of his Imperiall Maieſty. And in caſe that they cannot end it in loue, they ſhall haue liberty to enter a ſuite of Law, by the Aſſiſtance of the Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torall College, (whoſe preheminency his Imperial Maieſtie will alwayes reſpect and regard:) which ſuite, his Maieſtie ſhall further, advance, and ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as much as poſſibly in him lies; even in ſuch manner, as the ſayd interreſſed Pretenders can wiſh
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17884:20"/> themſelues, and their ſeverall pretenſions require; and that within a ſet and certaine time (which wee may appoint hereafter) the cauſe ſhall be ended and decided, according to the impartiall adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Iuſtice. His Maieſtie ſhall cauſe moreover, this clauſe to be inſerted into the Inveſtiture of the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> viz. <hi>That the ſame ſhall not bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall to the Emperour, the Roman Empire, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Palatine, his brother, or to the Count Palatine Wolff-wilhelmus Duke of Newburgh, or to all or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinſmen of his: and that all and every ones right and pretenſions (for ſo much as ſhall belong vnto them) ſhall remaine vnpreiudiced, and ſhall expreſly be reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and ſhall vpon the firſt opportunity be ended, either by the way of friendly comprimiſe, or legall proceeding. That ſo, whenſoever the Electorate ſhall be adiudged vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the children or kinſmen of the Palſgraue, they ſhal en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy that which ſhall be adiudged: and be inveſted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by his Imperial Maieſtie after the death of the Duke of Bavaria.</hi> And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Duke of Bavaria hath given his conſent to all this, and hath promiſed to carry him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe accordingly, and to put in ſufficient ſecurity for the ſame, by a Covenant of an Inſtrument Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall; as is vſed in ſuch like caſes. Whereby hee hath moſt effectually ſhewne how much he is encli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the well fare of his. Imperiall Maieſtie, the States of the ſacred Roman Empire, and to a firme peace and concord.</p>
               <p>And hereunto is his Maieſtie conſtant; that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he would doe nothing that might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the golden Bull, or his owne Capitulation Royall; but is fully perſwaded on the other ſide, that the Electorſhip is devolved vnto him, &amp; that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17884:21"/> hee accordingly may diſpoſe of it: nevertheleſſe, hee offers; that in regard of the children and kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the <hi>Palſgraue,</hi> to appoint a ſet Treatie for it, that it may be finally decided, either by loue or law, as hath been ſayd heretofore. By which, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Electors, Princes, and Ambaſſadours, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue his Maieſties care for the publique welfare.</p>
               <p>Moreover, his Maieſtie hath had a ſpecial care to ſupply the Electorall colledge, and doubts not, but that when the Temporall Electors (with whom he would gladly haue communicated himſelfe, if he might haue enioyed their companies) ſhall bee fully informed of all, as his Maieſtie purpoſes to ſend them word of it; but that they will bee very well pleaſed with his Maieſties milde delaration, &amp; his vnpreiudiciall diſpoſition; and that they wil likewiſe confirme the ſame by their voyces, as the Spirituall Electors haue done: Seeing that the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of a good and a ſtable peace in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, concerneth them, no leſſe then the other. To whom, with the Electors and Princes preſent, and the Ambaſſadors of thoſe that are abſent, his Imperial Maieſtie once againe promiſeth all friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Imperiall fauour, and all good offices.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Dated at Regenſpurgh, with the Imperiall Seale appending,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>the</hi> 23. <hi>of February.</hi> 1622.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
